Finding Aid for UAW-Ford University Records, 1995-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
UAW-Ford University Records 1995-2001
UAW-Ford University.
03113 Bq 2
A distance education program designed to provide "university-style approach to workplace education and training" for Ford auto plant workers. Developed at the University of Michigan the Institute for Labor and Industrial Relations (ILIR), and the UM-Dearborn College of Arts, Sciences, and Letters, the program is now centered at University of Michigan-Dearborn. Records include material on the founding of the program and some curriculum material.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
1.5 linear feet
The records (Donor no. 9142 ) were received in September 2001 through the University of Michigan School of Social Work
The record group is open to research.
The United Auto Workers-Ford Motor Company (UAW-Ford) University was an outgrowth of programs in the School of Social Work that provided educational counseling to UAW members in Ford plants. In 1996, following a UAW-Ford collective bargaining agreement calling for "a new program dedicated to a university-style approach to workplace education and training," the Institute for Labor and Industrial Relations (ILIR), and the UM-Dearborn College of Arts, Sciences, and Letters (CASL) responded with the "Work, Technology and Society Program." This distance education program is now centered at UM-Dearborn.
One of the key parts of UAW-Ford University was the development of a liberal arts degree program oriented to the auto industry, with plant-based educational programming and distance learning. This project began in 1997, and by Fall of 1998 courses in a new degree program were being offered on a pilot basis in three auto plants. The plan was to expand the project to additional plants, eventually making courses available throughout the UAW-Ford system nationally. The University of Michigan drew upon the resources of both its Ann Arbor and Dearborn campuses in developing this program.
The process of developing the degree program began with a union-management team from the UAW-Ford National Programs Center and a group of faculty and staff at the university. Plant-level studies were undertaken with local plants while a faculty advisory committee lead the curriculum development process within the university.
Several principles set the stage for development. First, there was general agreement that the courses should use Internet technologies with the goal of becoming an online, virtual university. Second, two-way video technology would be used as a transitional approach. Third, courses on CD-ROM and the Internet would be developed as models to be tested for future expansion. Technology was a key instrument for the program. All of the courses were to use computer applications for assignments, access to research collections, class discussion, communications with professors, and other traditional parts of the curriculum.
Student support services was a key area for the implementation of the distance learning enterprise. Three resources for students support services are part of the program: Education Training Coordinators (ETC), Skills Enhancement Program (SEP), and Education Resource Specialists (ERS). The ETCs were in-plant education advisor who aided in recruiting and registering students and provided a range of individualized support. The SEP was an in-plant education center which provides general educational support and assistance with computer skills. Finally, the ERSs were advisors from the University of Michigan who worked directly with the UAW-Ford University program, providing academic advising. They also had a range of administrative and program development responsibilities. The ERSs, working with SEPs and ETCs, formed a network of support staff that engages in active outreach to provide assistance to students.
The UAW Ford University is now a virtual university with a network of accredited colleges and universities that offer courses, certificates, and various degree options using the latest technologies to expand educational opportunities offered to UAW-represented employees. http://www.uawford.com/UFU/Intro.cfm
* Much of the information contained in this history was taken from "Long Summary" in the History and Proposals series, and the University Record article "Units collaborate to offer on-site or at-home courses for Ford workers," October 11, 1999.
The UAW-Ford University record group covers the period from 1995 to 2001 and primarily represents the involvement of the University of Michigan School of Social Work in the development and early administration of the UAW-Ford University and efforts at developing educational counseling and distance education programs. Materials include planning files, CD-ROMs containing examples of curriculum and resources, and various proposals and reports. The records are organized into five series: History and Proposals, Reports, Meetings, Plant-level Studies and Educational Resources.
Subjects:
UAW-Ford University.; Employees--Training of--Michigan.; Distance education--Computer-assisted instruction.; Automobile industry workers--Labor unions--United States.; Ford Motor Company--Employees.; International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America.; University of Michigan. School of Social Work.; University of Michigan--Dearborn.
- History and Proposals
  The History and Proposals series contains correspondence and information regarding the establishment and development of the program. It also contains information about the Smithsonian Award given to UAW-Ford University in 1999. This award is dedicated to persons, organizations and institutions that are leading the information technology revolution. Proposals about budget and continuation activities are also part of this series.
  - UAW-Ford University History (Box 1)
  - Distance Learning Presentation; Northwest Ohio College Council April 28, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding program establishment and development 1996-1997, 1998, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Educating Employees for the Twenty First Century October 28, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Proposals 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Proposed Budget 1997-2000 (Box 1)
  - Proposal for Continuation Activities 1997, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Smithsonian Award Case Study Submission 1999 (Box 1)
  - Smithsonian Award Ceremony 1999 (Box 1)
  - UAW-Ford University Model and Applications January 1996 (Box 1)
- Reports
  The Reports series contains monthly progress reports about the UAW-Ford University development. It also contains evaluation reports from the Fall and Winter terms in the period 1997-1999. Each evaluation report presents an executive summary, findings and recommendations, individual reports and appendixes with data collection, course descriptions and student statistics. The evaluation reports present a complete overview of the development of the program and recommendations to improve it. There are also in this series, research reports, reports on student progress and planning documents.
  - Evaluation Reports 1997-1999, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Marketing Strategies 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Monthly Progress Reports 1998-2001, 23 folders (Box 1)
  - Planning Documents 1997-1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Report to National Programs Center (NPC) 1998 (Box 1)
  - Research Reports
    - Benchmarking Activities and the Implications for UAW-Ford University November 30, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Leadership Perspectives, May 6,1999 (Box 1)
    - Renewal Application for Review of Research Protocols Involving Human Subjects 1996-2000 (Box 1)
    - Research for UAW-Ford University Planning: Comparison and Programs, June 30,1999 (Box 1)
  - Statistics and Reports on Students Progress 1997-2000 (Box 1)
  - Status and Accomplishment Summaries 1996-1999 (Box 1)
  - UM-Dearborn Transition Planning Report April 2001 (Box 1)
- Meetings 1997-2000
  The Meetings series, 1997-2000, contains minutes from the meetings between UAW-Ford National Programs Center (NPC) and the University of Michigan, including meetings with plant representatives.
  - UAW-Ford NPC and UM 1997-2000, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - UAW-Ford NPC, UM and SABCO October 1997 (Box 1)
  - UAW-Ford NPC, UM, Livonia Transmission Plant, Louisville Assembly Plant and Sterling Plant November 10, 1997 (Box 1)
  - UAW-Ford NPC, UM and SAMCO April 20, 1998 (Box 1)
  - UFU Team, Skills Enhancement Program (SEP) Team and UM May 13, 1998 (Box 1)
  - NPC Meeting: Presentation Material September 1, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Orientation Meeting-Walton Hills February 8, 2000 (Box 1)
- Plant-level Studies 1996-1999
  The Plant-level Studies series, 1996-1999, contains guidelines used for interviews and focus groups. It also includes information about plans to implement plant-level studies in different locations.
  - Focus Groups Guidelines 1997-1999 (Box 2)
  - Implementation Plan 1998 (Box 2)
  - Interview Guidelines 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - Orientation Meeting with Local 723/Monroe regarding Local Plant-level Studies 1999 (Box 2)
  - Local Plant Studies Preliminary Reports 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - Sampling Workers and Survey 1996-1998 (Box 2)
- Educational Resources 1999-2000
  The Educational Resources series includes information about course offerings, student services and the distance learning program. CD-ROMs from some courses offered in 2000 are part of this series. Each CD-ROM contains a full presentation of the course using video and presentation slides. The media was recorded in Real Networks G2 format. The CD-ROMs are prime examples of the courses and content developed to meet distance education needs and utilize current technologies. The series also includes a videotape about the articulation agreement signing between the Lorain County Community College and the University of Michigan-Dearborn.
  - Articulation Agreement Signings 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Videotape (VHS): Articulation Agreement Signing, Lorain County Community College and UM-Dearborn July 27, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Auto Industry Degree Goals and Potential Course Offerings May 1996 (Box 2)
  - Community Colleges 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence regarding educational programs 1999 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence to students regarding educational information 1998-2000 (Box 2)
  - Course CDs (format: Real Player) 2000, 2 folders
    - ENGL 232, Sheryl Pearson (Box 2)
    - History of Industrial Technology (Box 2)
    - Sociology 443, James Gruber, Ph.D. (Box 2)
    - Psychology 320, Pamela McAuslan, Ph.D. D (Box 2)
    - Psychology 430, Marie Waung, 2 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Course Offerings 1998-2001 (Box 2)
  - Distance Learning Program
    - General Information (Box 2)
    - Promotions and Brochures (Box 2)
  - Program Expansion Plan 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Project Guidelines for Student Services January 2001 (Box 2)
  - Promotions
    - Certificates of Achievement and Registration (Box 2)
    - Handouts and Brochures (Box 2)
  - Student Handbook 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Student Services, Education Resource Specialists (ERS) and Skills Enhancement Program (SEP) 1997, 1999-2001 (Box 2)
  - Technology Tutorials 2000 (Box 2)
  - Transfer Guide for Associate Degree Students June 2000 (Box 2)
  - UAW-Ford University On-line
    - Promotional Strategies Guides July 20, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Student Resources (Box 2)
    - Web Site 2001 (Box 2)
Related Material
Researchers interested in this program and educational initiatives in auto plants should also consult the following related record groups: University of Michigan School of Social Work-UAW-GM Educational Development Counseling Program, and the University of Michigan Employment Transition Program.
In 1999, UAW-Ford University received a Computerworld Smithsonian Award. The project is part of the Smithsonian Institution's Permanent Research Collection on Information Technology and part of an exhibit on the history of information technology.